[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host jaavan as proni and
today I'm joined by Kent Beck for a
conversation on software design based on
his latest book tidy first with a
question Mark at the end Kent is the
creator of extreme programming a pioneer
of software patterns and a co-author of
junit he rediscovered test driven
development and is an observer of 3x
explore expand extract he's a signatory
of the agile Manifesto and currently is
the chief scientist at mechanical
Orchard he authored several books on
Extreme programming test driven
development and patterns and of course
tid the first Kent welcome to software
engineering radio is there anything amem
miss that you'd like to add CIA Joe it's
good to be with you this San Francisco
morning now I think that about covers it
as far as the Computing world is
concerned okay then let's start so first
of all let's talk about the reasons for
writing the book yeah yeah so reading
your book you wrote there that your aim
was to bring to today's audience the
contents of the book structure designed
by uron and Constantine which you call
the Bible of software engineering can
you tell us a bit more about that when I
was in college I had this brand new book
as a text book called structure design
it's a green cover if you had it in
college you you fear this book as well
and because it oh you have a copy
fantastic because it was a college
textbook of course I I only read the
assigned parts and I read them as
quickly as necessary to pass the test so
I didn't really absorb everything that
was or much of what was in the book and
then in 2005 I was invited to be on a
panel with Ed rest in peace and Larry to
discuss the 25th anniversary of the book
so I thought well I better read it and I
read it cover to cover and it was an
absolute page Turner to me and what I
discovered as I was reading it was
their laid out were the basic
fundamental laws like Newton's laws of
physics but for software
engineering the challenge is the
examples are ancient you know there's a
discussion of paper tape as a storage
medium there's a discussion of the big
debate between Assembly Language and
higher level languages it's just really
hard for a modern reader to read it and
so I said well I'm going to translate
but the information was absolutely
fundamental coupling and cohesion is all
laid out there why software is so damn
expensive and what you can do about it
they understood all this stuff and our
understanding of those basic principles
is sort of been handed down one person
to the next to the next and gotten very
diffused so that was the point at which
I said okay I really do need to write a
book that brings this information to a
modern
readership the decision to write the
book so I read it cover to cover I also
have to tell you that I was using some
markers in the book to say okay what can
I ask you during the interview I ended
up marking everything so I had to cut
down content but one thing that I read
as well which I always do in books is
also the references and in the
references he wrote something about a
book of a philosophy of software design
by John oout which I paraphrase you said
that in that book that prompted you to
write Teddy
first because he makes uh some good
points points well taken but they are
presented dogmatically can you explain
us what you mean so it's deeply
satisfying as a programmer to take some
messy code and clean it up that activity
just feels good to somebody with a
programming kind of
mindset and philosophy of software
design says okay well if you know how to
clean up the software always clean it up
and that just seems to me to be not the
whole story that there are pressures
there's legitimate pressures that cause
you to leave software in a messy State
and part of the skill of being a
designer is knowing how to sense those
pressures and when to give into them but
also sense those pressures and knowing
when to Buck them so somebody says you
finish a feature they say they want the
next feature you
say not quite before I implement this
feature I'm going to tidy first and that
that's a design decision the decision
whether or not to design is as much a
design decision as the decision of how
to arrange the modules and services and
functions and statements in the
functions and so on and so forth so that
was my objection to that book I love
it's a slim little book which you've
been kind enough not to mention tidy
first there's not a lot of pages in
there I don't apologize for that I only
wrote about the things that I felt that
I understood well and that would be most
important it's not every important topic
about software design but I saved you a
bunch of hours of reading through stuff
that wasn't important so you're welcome
in the book you st also another thing
that you said that much does and advice
just flat out contradicts available
evidence so can you expand on that maybe
with some examples as well sure the
simplest example is when people talk
about
averages of metrics that don't converge
so for example what is the distribution
of the number of lines per function
somebody might say well you know
functions should be no more than 7 plus
or minus 2 you know is just some magic
number pulled out of one context and put
into a different context but if you look
at the actual distribution of number of
lines per function it doesn't look like
that at all in any software even if you
write it with that rule in mind it's
still going to be distributed in
something that looks more like a power
law and one of the characteristics of
power laws is that they don't converge
the central limit theirm doesn't hold
there's no mean
length of
functions the more functions you have
the larger the mean is going to be and
that's just a natural law it's it's like
asking what's the average size of
avalanches or what's the average size of
hurricanes the more hurricanes that you
measure the higher the average intensity
is going to be that's just natural law
and so that's that's something I wanted
to bring to the conversation about
software design is this is actually a
natural process and you and I are
instruments of the expression of that
natural process we have influence over
it but we don't have control over we
can't just design the software any way
we want because there are these Natural
Forces impinging on the decisions that
we make and we can't escape those so if
anybody says you know the maximum size
whatever the maximum number of functions
module the maximum number of parameters
per function or something like that they
don't understand that what they're
dealing with is a natural process and
that and that that mean of the number of
parameters or the max of the number of
parameters the bigger the system is the
bigger both of those numbers are going
to be yeah the power losss in software
seem to be pretty much everywhere yes
the runtime of tests the number of times
a test fails just over and over again
I've been pursuing these distributions
for 20 25 years just because I'm
fascinated by them and you know I'm not
sure it's entirely a healthy or sane
approach but there you
go and now let's go a bit more into
let's say the main subject if you like
of the book or the main concept so let's
start from the three main Concepts I
think around which the book evolves you
know there is cohesion coupling and
tidings and then of course there is
everything that comes out you know
design and everything else but let's
start with this so first question for me
is can you briefly give our audience a
refresher on cohesion and coupling what
they are sure and these words have come
to mean much fuzzier Concepts over time
so I'm returning to the original
definitions from Jordin and
Constantine and from Jordin and
Constantine coupling is coupling with
respect to a change that you want to
make is if I change one element I have
to change the other
element if so then those two elements
are coupling so for example if one
function calls another they are coupled
with respect to changes to the name of
the function that's called if I change
the the Declaration of the function I
have to go change all the callers too so
a calling function is coupled to the
called function with respect to changes
of the name and vice versa if I want to
change the name at the call site I'm
going to have to go change the name at
the implementation too so those two
elements and I say elements because this
is fractal it goes all the way from two
expressions in a statement two
statements in a function two functions
in a class two classes in a module two
modules in a service it's up and down
and up and down down coupling is a
relationship between elements where
changing one of them requires that you
change another one and cohesion cohesion
okay so this is what took me 18 years to
write this book and it was being able to
explain cohes that I just I'm very
stubborn so I kept going and kept going
until I could actually explain it so
inside of an element so let's say inside
of a file you have a bunch of functions
that file is cohesive if the functions
are coupled if I change one of the
functions I have to change all the other
ones then the file is cohesive and if so
imagine you have a function with a 100
lines and you always change the same two
lines in that function but you don't
change the other 98 lines that function
is not cohesive because there's a bunch
of stuff that doesn't change and and a
couple of statements that do change so
you might say well that's bad we don't
want coupling because it's expensive and
it sets up these cascading changes which
is what drives the cost so what you
would do if you wanted to improve the
design of that system is you take the
two lines that change all the time and
you would extract them as their own
little helper function and then when you
need to go make changes you just have to
change those two lines you don't have to
change two out of 100 lines you might
say well but I don't want to have to
change those two lines together and the
answer is well sometimes there's
coupling and you can't get rid of all of
it because you can't predict what all
changes you're going to want to make and
remember the coupling works with respect
to particular changes that you want to
make so you can't get rid of it but you
can sweep it all into one pile and
that's what cohesion is about it's about
limiting the potential spread of
coupling okay and now the concept that
gives the title to the book so a Tiding
the question is what is a tithing I mean
in the book also list 15 of them so you
can tell us what it is and maybe give us
some examples of Tidings sure so this is
a pedagogical choice on my part this
this is not the last word on software
design this is the first of three
proposed books and pedagogically I
decided let me start at the smallest
scale of design so people can get lots
and lots of practice working design into
their regular workflows so the that
phrase tidy first is uh situation that
we all encounter 10 times a day as a
programmer I need to change the behavior
of some code but it's messy and it's
going to be hard to change because I
can't see what the contr control flow is
or the names are wrong or just badly
formatted or there's something you know
it's producing the numbers that it's
producing but it's structured in a way
that's hard to change and so you're left
with this dilemma should I TI first and
that's why you the question mark in the
title which if you're an author I'm
going to warn you please never put
punctuation in the title of the book
it's turned out to be a disaster but
there you go so I need to change this
code it's messy should I tidy first and
the answer is maybe sometimes yes and
sometimes no that's the kind of answer
that the philosophy of software design
doesn't give you to go back to an
earlier point but you have to decide
okay well should I tidy this up first
and there are programmers who do it by
habit there are programmers who never do
it and I don't think either of those is
the optimal solution yeah an example of
a tithing just to give an idea people
you know because we are talking about
cleaning up things tidying up so
rationalizing a name you see a name of a
variable and it doesn't make any sense
to you and then you understand the code
and a tiing would be to just fix that
name yeah so now you've changed the
structure of the code but you haven't
changed Its Behavior at all it's going
to compute exactly the same outputs for
the same inputs but now it's less messy
it's easier for you to understand yeah
so you does now that you just mentioned
the behavior and the structure so
Tidings are purely structural in corre
what they achieve so they don't change
any Behavior at all yeah yeah absolutely
not and that's part of the thesis of the
book or the the whole style that I'm I'm
advocating here is you make a strong
distinction between the changes to the
structure of the system and changes to
the behavior of the system and you never
mix the two together you might alternate
every three minutes but you're never
changing a name adding an if statement
swapping the sense of test of something
all at the same time there's too many
chances for errors and errors sap your
confidence and you lose the confidence
of your teammates and down it goes so
Tidings also I think you say this in the
book are kind of small
refactorings correct unfortunately
refactoring has drifted a long ways from
its original definition people will say
oh well I need to refactor and they're
changing the structure and the behavior
of the system in sometimes unpredictable
ways and I absolutely don't want to do
that if I'm working on the structure if
I got the structure hat on I'm just
working on the structure I got a
question that is maybe out of my
personal curiosity more than anything
else so to me tidings look a lot like
patterns in the way you describe them
it's like you can do this and then you
tell people but watch out on when to do
them you may consider that so I've got
this impression that you know also the
work you did on pattern somehow has an
influence here oh 100% once I started to
see repeating
decisions with consistent sets of uh
posing constraints and that's what a
pattern is I can't unsee it so just in
see the world and seeing my work I'm
seeing it in terms of those sorts of
patterns and yeah it turns out that
there really are those kinds of
repeating patterns and if you pay close
attention to them you can do a much
better job of making those repeating
decisions if you look at them in terms
of the conflicting sets of conflicting
forces that act on them going back to
the design so I'm interested in
understanding what maybe in giving maybe
the audience some examp of the actual
practical effects of Tidings because
they are small changes yeah tiny often
very tiny you know rename a variable
maybe groups UN code differently add a
break a white line in between two groups
of statements and to clarify the meaning
or things like this but in practice if I
understand it correctly they can have
quite dramatic effects when you compound
them in terms of code quality can you
tell us a bit more about it and maybe
some examples from real software World
sure and so that is part of the
underlying assumptions of this I call it
empirical software design this empirical
style is that small changes
compound and every once in a while so
this is this is an effect I think most
people who've tried to design it in
style have noticed most of the time you
make a little change to the structure
and it has a small effect and make
another little change it has a small
effect and then you make a little change
seems like just another little change
and then it has a small effect but then
you see oh but that lets me do this and
then that lets me do that and then I can
do those two things and then I can get
rid of all this whole
blah but what triggered that was just
that one little snowflake flopping over
and then you end up with an avalin when
I say let's make large changes in small
safe steps that's the kind of effect
that I'm taking advantage of so an
example there was a feature that was
introduced late in junit 4 called now
I'm going to it's been a while since I
worked on that code where you could wrap
tests in an object and this was good for
precondition post conditions it was good
people rules they're called
rules
anyway that
feature which was a a big deal at the
time it was released
was the result of a bunch of teeny tiny
changes we had this really complicated
chain of functions that called each
other and we just started to turn each
one into its own object and then we
nested the objects and then we said oh
it would be so easy to add another
object to this chain and it was a big
feature but the actual implementation of
it was
small and we had set ourselves up for
that
kind of like Jenga you know where you
pull the you know you set yourself up
you you pull out the things that keep
you from implementing this function part
of the philosophy is this phrase I came
up with for each hard change make the
change easy then make the easy change as
opposed to sweating and straining to
make really difficult changes which
inexperienced programmers tend to do so
you pull out these jangle blocks and
then you pull out the last when the
whole thing comes tumbling down but it's
you didn't bring in a bulldozzer and
knock the whole edifice over you just
made small changes small changes and
then you made a small change that had a
very large effect yeah and another thing
is making all these changes one after
the other I guess probably as an effect
of the power losss we deal with exactly
right is also you end up touching I
think you mentioned this the code you
keep touching all the time is is pretty
much clean so the Cod that is not clean
is the one that you don't touch simply
because because of this power losss you
keep working pretty much on the same
area most of the time yeah St paredo
comes to our rescue once again in this
so programmers some programmers have
this fairy tale that they tell
themselves about how the whole system
could be tight clean and not messy at
all and completely tighten and just no
software like that there's always parts
that are better and parts that are worse
and there's
parts that are improving and there are
parts that are getting worse that's the
nature of it it's more like a garden
than it is like some perfect
sculpture and because of that if you
haven't been tidying when you start
tidying you're overwhelmed by all the
messes you start to see and that's part
of that question tidy first is realizing
okay well I'm GNA tidy around here
because I need to make changes here and
I see a bunch more Tidings and I'm going
to choose not to do those just yet but
you know Paro says 80% of the changes
are going to happen in 20% of the code
if you adopt this kind of tidying in
your local area most of the code that
you change most of the time is going to
be well
structured and yeah there's parts of it
that you still might be embarrassed
about or ashamed of or would be
difficult to change if only you had to
change it but you probably statistically
speaking not going to have to change it
so it doesn't have any practical effect
yeah and now maybe a bit of a you may
see that as a provocative question if
you like why not use big refactorings
instead well the first line I wrote in
this book was software design is an
exercise in human relationships
what I wrote that and I thought that
doesn't make any sense it's you know
about coupling and cohesion all about
power laws is but the more I thought
about it the more I realized if the
Human
Relationships that affect software
development aren't healthy the software
is not going to be
healthy and what's fundamentally wrong
with these pause refactorings I don't
have a good name for these but I'll work
on it these you know where you say oh we
need to
to get this cleaned up is the effect
that it has on the Human Relationships
that might be the most efficient way to
do the to make the changes that you want
to make but if your users or your
managers or your product people say oh
those programmers they you know we they
can't be trusted they just you know go
away for a month they say they're
working really hard but when they come
back the system does exactly the best
case scenario is the system does exactly
what it did
before why did I wait a month for that I
could have had a bunch of features and
that damages the relationship so part of
the skill of empirical software
design is this being able to make you
can't if you're on radio you can't see
me lacing my fingers together but to
make the structure changes and the
behavior changes in small enough steps
so that from the outside it looks like
you're just working on features or
you're just working on design but inside
you know you're going back and forth and
back and forth and back and forth and
back and forth yeah and I think another
problem that I've seen at least with the
biger factorings is that sometimes they
are done in arbitary places in code code
that just looks ugly but it's not
necessarily the code that you're are
going to touch later to implement new
functionality correct so it's it's like
insisting that I I'm going to go down to
my basement and there's a pile of stuff
in the corner that just doesn't bother
me I no but I need to go down there and
change it now I'm a little OCD and I
understand the satisfaction of cleaning
up the you know the corner of the garage
but practically speaking if you're
getting paid for the work it's probably
not the highest priority
yes going back to structural and
behavioral changes so tidings we said
you know refactoring so they are
structural changes how do they relate
with behavioral changes I think we
hinted at that when we were talking
about composing them and so when you
gave the example of junit 4 can we
expand a bit on this well if you look at
some code let's say we have to change
two functions in a file and one is at
the beginning of the file and the other
is at the end of the file so the two
functions are coupled according to our
earlier definition but the file is not
cohesive because I only have to change
these two functions and the functions
aren't even next to each other there's
10 other functions in between them I can
just change function a and then change
function B and I'm all
done but I'm going to have to navigate
between the two maybe I have to bring
them up side by side you know in two
editors so that I can see how the two
are changing at the same time so I could
do that and it would take me a certain
amount of time and I'd have a certain
probability of making a mistake in the
process and so on or I can tidy
first and the Tidy first in there just
the the simplest littlest change that's
going to make the behavior change we
want to make easier is to take the two
functions and put them together maybe
the two go together at the top maybe the
two go together at the bottom B maybe
they go someplace in the middle I don't
care but if the first thing I do is
reorder the functions in the file that's
the
tidying I'm done I'm finished I can
deploy that to production it's perfectly
safe if it's not perfectly safe do it in
smaller
steps so now I've done that tidying and
now I've made the change
easier now I make the slightly easier
change so every time you're GNA make a
behavior change if it feels harder than
it really needs to be I want to ask
myself should I tidy first and the
answer is sometimes yes and sometimes no
now sometimes you'll make a behavior
change and then that leaves things kind
of messy and then you tidy afterwards
and that's fine to do a little bit of it
and then sometimes you know you don't
have anything pressing and there is a
corner of the of the garage and or the
basement and you just go and tidy it
just because but only a little bit and
realize that you're indulging yourself
as you're
doing but also I guess there could be
the case also sometimes some
Tidings let you see things that you are
not seeing before I don't know something
you extract the helper or yeah yeah 100%
you change some names and now you
realize oh this code here is exactly
like that code there I couldn't see the
similarity because the names were
gratuitously different and then I fix
that now I see oh that's really doing
exactly the same thing and now I can
unify the two and I can reduce coupling
yeah um another thing that I find
interesting is this difference between
the structural and behavioral changes
the reversibility aspect so you say that
structural changes are generally
reversible I mean most of the time maybe
depending on the side but behavioral
ones are often not reversible so can you
give us some examples sure Jeff Bezos
talks about the type one and type two
decisions it's the same the same concept
and when you need to make a decision one
thing to notice is whether you can undo
that decision easily if you can undo a
decision easily you don't have to
carefully analyze should I do this you
know people spend more time analyzing
the potential effects of a decision than
they will actually making the decision
if it's reversible that makes no sense
just do it so I think that these four
lines would make a good helper function
just extract it just see and if you have
proper tooling that's going to be a snap
it'll have zero chance of breaking
anything just do it because if you don't
like it you can undo it you inline the
function because of course your ID has
really good refactoring
support uh
some do and some don't and so those
changes are easily reversible so they
don't need to be carefully analyzed and
thought through before you execute them
Behavior changes on the other hand have
effects in the outside world you make it
so new users can't sign up or you report
the wrong numbers to the tax Authority
or you make payouts incorrectly or you
ship things to the wrong address all
those are effects in the world that
aren't easily reversible and so you
should take extra care when making those
irreversible decisions the mistake
people make is they think well you know
we structur is like this and we'd like
it like that and so we're going to sit
and think really carefully about whether
we should do that no start moving the
structure from how it is to how you
think it should be if you discover
that's the the wrong direction you can
easily reverse it so don't treat those
decisions the same way that you treat
the decisions that have irreversible
effects in the outside world where you
want unit tests and functional tests and
you want to double check with the users
and you want to roll it out a little bit
at a time and all all that stuff that's
all to prevent irreversible effects
there are also some Tidings or
structural changes that can be
irreversible or or very difficult to
revert I things that come to my mind I
don't know anything if you rename an API
you don't change the behavior but give
it a different name or I don't know
change the url of NH https call rest
call or things like this so also with
structural changes there is a chance
that depending on the change even if the
behavior is the same the change might be
very difficult to revert am I correct in
this yes so working on junit we spent
more energy on backwards compatibility
than we did on new features just in
terms of engineering hours and that's
because there were billions tens of
billions of dollars worth of tests out
there that relied on one set of apis and
we just didn't want to break those so
the key trick there is to have two
versions at in parallel at the same time
you know and this is the standard
deprecation thing which says okay you're
calling this function you should call
this function instead but we're still
going to make sure that the software
Works while we're in this transition
period that makes that decision to a
degree reversible because if you decide
then the new way is is bad then you may
be able to go back to the old way now
you you can get stuck with one foot on
the dock and one foot in in the boat
where you have the old API and the new
API and you have to maintain them both
and they're getting further and further
apart and that's quite uncomfortable but
you try and avoid that by working in
small safe steps to the degree that you
can but yes those decisions that leak
out into the out outside world those
designed decisions that leak out into
the outside world those become your
reversible and so you need to take a
different process thinking about them
than you do about the one where that are
cohesive where you can control how the
the coupling goes so that HTTP call is
coupled with respect to the names of
parameters and the name in the URL if
you want to change the url you'd have to
change all those colar and there might
be millions of them and you don't have
any control over them so you have
coupling there that constrains the kind
of changes that you can make so you'd
like to take that coupling and make it
in as small an area as possible what
about the architecture of the of a
system you know Tidings are small things
yeah small changes tiny things then we
talk about how they compose and can
actually enable bigger changes so what
is the relationship with the
architecture of a system and the
tidings so to me design is fractal it's
about you have these elements they have
relationships the relationships benefit
the elements not the elephants coffee
has not quite kicked in yet the
relationship you know if I have a
function and it can be simpler because I
can call this helper function now that
there's benefit in that relationship
between those two functions I don't see
any reason to differentiate from the
perspective of principle between
elements that are like two
services in a big system and two
expressions that are in the same
statement I don't see those as
fundamentally different things the same
principles coupling and cohesion apply
reversibility and irreversibility power
laws apply at all those different scales
that's hence that word scale free you
want to make changes in small safe steps
it's an exercise in human relationships
like all the principles still apply it's
just the scale at which you work is is
different and what about the
relationship with design you know how
much do we need to design say up front
you know okay you're trying to hook me
in here so the more comfortable you
are making changes to the structure of a
running system the less need you have to
design upfront the problem with
designing upfront is you're making
decisions in conditions of Maximum
uncertainty and minim minimum of
knowledge so in this empirical style you
want to minimize the decisions that you
make when they're really likely to be
wrong now I don't people disagree with
this and God bless them but I don't
understand why you would insist on
making the maximum number of decisions
in conditions of Maximum uncertainty and
and minimum knowledge I just I I don't
get it there is this Fe okay we're going
to get this system into production it's
going to have a horrible design and
we'll never be able to fix it and I
don't accept that premise I think that
if you take good care of the
relationships between designers and
users and managers and investors and so
if you take good care of those
relationships you will have time to do
the design the whole thing is not going
to be beautiful and tidy yeah exactly
right but all software that's making
money is messy and if it's not making
money or not yielding a return you know
for open source projects then who cares
also imagine that if you put enough you
know safety nets around you maybe being
a bit disciplined with having test
automation automation for deployments
and things like this making changes to a
system that is in production becomes a
bit easier I'm not saying that is easy
but easier than if you lack this
discipline right and the practices that
you just listed are all part of making
the change easy now let's go to
discussing when to tithe you know the
the question
mark correct yeah so one thing that I
find interesting and I can relate to I
have to say is that your focus not only
on the quality of the code yeah which
seems to be the case with many software
design books you know focus on the code
and the structure of the system and how
thing you know cohesion and coupling but
a bit in a in a context free situation
if you like and so you said well the
answer to tidy first or after or later
or never depends on several forces so
you mention cost Revenue coupling and
cohesion I think these are the main ones
you mentioned can you tell us more about
that
sure so one of the reasons that strategy
of Designing upfront runs into a lot of
resistance I want to be careful how I
critique it one of the reasons that is
that that upfront design runs contrary
to the economic forces that are driving
your
software and the two big economic forces
that push against designing up front one
is just the survivability of the system
the sooner you can get some features in
there creating Revenue getting people
using it the more likely your software
is to survive that's one factor and if
if you say well but I'm going to spend
three months designing it before I
implement the first
feature software might not survive three
months with no features so yeah it might
be nice to go off and get all the design
worked out before you start implementing
stuff but if the Project's cancelled as
a
result why did you do that the second
one though is is this a time value of
money The Net Present Value and if
you're a programmer and you don't know
what npv is I strongly urge you to look
it up and then play with it so this
happened to me probably 25 or 30 years
ago I'd have these discussions where I
had perfectly good engineering reasons
for wanting to do what I want to do and
the business people would just like what
are you even talking about makes no
sense somebody mentioned about the time
value of money oh this was probably when
I was working on insurance
products and I built spread sheets and I
started playing with the net present
value and my eyes were open and this is
the idea that uh money sooner is the
same as more money so if if you revenue
revenue sooner is the same as as more
Revenue cost later is the same as lower
cost and right now we have relatively
High interest rates compared to the last
10 years and so this effect is Amplified
and this is the idea that if I can get
Revenue sooner I can earn interest on
the money that I made so that's the same
as if I earned more money but I earned
it later the design UPF front is cost
it's going to have future benefits we
promise but they're going to happen
later so we have to make a lot more
money later than we made now in order to
make up for the delay in achieving that
Revenue it's also costs that happen
sooner so those costs are Amplified in
today's perspective compared to if we
took that same amount of investment and
we spread it o in payments over time so
when somebody says well I want to I want
to design the everything right up front
I think one you're increasing the chance
of their Project's just going to die and
two you're working against the time
value of money which the business people
understand and I as a programmer had
never encountered and I didn't
understand it so even even though you're
that has a kind of intuitive appeal to
me as an engineer it it just goes
against the context in which I'm working
and that context isn't going to change
if I adapt my style of working to the
context that I'm actually working in
things are going to go more smoothly I'm
going to have an easier time doing what
I'm doing this applies to the tidings as
well then so the decision of basically
tithing first later or never I guess is
in this context as well sometimes it's a
no-brainer I have some messy code it
would take me a half an hour to figure
it out and make some changes if I spend
10 minutes tidying then I can spend 10
minutes making those same changes okay
no brainer I should definitely tidy
first for sure sometimes it's kind of uh
I can tidy for 15 minutes and then spend
15 minutes making the change or I can
spend 30 minutes making changes to the
messy coat probably in that case it's
still in your best interest to tidy it
because somebody else is likely to
change that same code in the future and
they'll reap the benefits of the tidings
that you make it's when the potential
benefits of the tidings push out further
and further like well over the next
three years we're going to recover the
cost and that's why the bias in tidy
first is I'm going to make the changes
to the structure right where I want to
make the changes to the behavior and I'm
going to be increasingly
suspicious of making the changes that
ripple from there yeah makes perfect
sense um one thing that also I found
interesting is the constant equivalence
that you came up with which basically
state that c the cost of software and
coupling are essentially the same thing
now this is interesting because also
from what you said and all the things
you discussed also there is also cost in
decoupling as well which seems to be a
bit of a contradiction now how do we Sol
these one sure so Constantin equivalence
says the cost of software is mostly the
cost in changing the software this
upfront cost is a small fraction of the
money that you're going to spend on the
software overall but all those changes
aren't the same because of the power
laws we've talked about there's going to
be a few big changes that really
dominate the complete cost just as you
have a few gigantic hurricanes that
dominate the effects of hurricanes all
around the those big changes come
because there are changes that Ripple
through the system I change this oh that
means I have to change those two things
oh because I changed this other thing
and I have to change five more things B
and then you've got even though the
initial trigger was just let add one
more button to this this screen the
ripple effect went through the whole
system and became extremely expensive so
if you count up the cost of those
changes that set off an avalanche that's
a big proportion of the total cost of
changing the system so the cost of the
software is H roughly equivalent to the
cost of those big changes and those big
changes come about because of coupling
that's exactly the description of
coupling I Chang this so that I have to
change that too so if you squish all
those together the cost of software is
approximately the coupling in the system
but there's also cost involved in
decoupling the system because we're
going to have to make those structural
changes to get rid of the coupling so a
common move like this is I've got a
server and a client and I have some
protocol on The
Wire I write a interface definition
language used to be if I changed the
btes that went across the wire i' have
to change both sides so they're C with
respect to changes to the protocol if I
introduce an interface description
language now I only have to change the
IDL and the client in the server
automatically change so I have decoupled
those two but I've had to define the IDL
I've had to change the tooling I maybe I
change the deployment d d so there's
some cost to eliminating that coupling
and now you're in this trade-off space
where you have the cost that you're
paying for coupling and the cost that
you're paying for decoupling and it's
the sum of those two things that's the
cost of the software which is why
software design has such a centralized
role in the business of
software because you're juggling those
two factors how coupled is the system
how much would it cost to decouple it
and how will we can M maintain that
balance over time and talking about the
more implementation details let's say
that some people in in our audience say
okay you know what I want to look more
carefully when I Ty up code and maybe
follow an approach closer to what can
recommends yeah maybe a bit more
discipline with refactoring structural
changes and behavioral changes now one
of the things that of course you he
wrote about is how to push those changes
in the Repository so especially for
teams that use P requests and maybe code
reviews whole another topic yeah but go
ahead I won't ask about trank based
development I will just ask about this
okay good I will ask you the difficult
questions so what are your suggestions
here and maybe have you experimented
with it a bit and see if you have any
any
recommendations sure so one
recommendation is if you have to use
poll requests as I said I have strong
opinions about that which I won't get
into here if you're using that style if
you're working in in that kind of
workflow try as an experiment I'm not
saying this is the right thing to do I'm
saying this is a worthwhile experiment
try only having structure changes or
only having behavior changes in a single
pull request the structure changes
should be really easy to review I
extract some helper
method I'm done yeah the system's a
little bit better
that's a easy one to review might not
require review at all once you get some
experience doing
this if I have Behavior changes don't
mix structure changes in with them so my
behavior change is going to be here's a
new
test and then here's some changes to the
logic of the system without which the
test would fail with which the test
succeeds okay so that's again a
relatively easy change
to review it requires more review than
the structure changes because you have
to ask yourself questions like are there
other Corner cases that are aren't being
covered here is the test sufficient to
give me confidence that this is going to
work but only have one kind of change
per PR or if you want to you can have
multiple commits in a PR and each commit
could only have Behavior or structure
changes
you work it out but strictly separate
them now sometimes in your programming
you don't know exactly how you want to
implement or you can Implement something
so you're kind of fooling around and you
change some logic and then you see the
structure is a little wrong so you
change the structure and then you can
change some more logic easily and then
back and forth and back and forth and
what you end up with at the end of a few
hours is a a big jumble of
changes and part of this experiment that
I'm
suggesting is either you throw away what
you've done and you start over and in
this SB style where you're only making
structure or only making Behavior
changes at a given time or you look at
all of the changes that you made in that
three or four hours of wandering around
and you pull it apart you retroactively
apply this
rationalizing model where there's a
beautiful parnas paper called a rational
design method and how and why to fake it
that's it's exactly this where you say
okay well you know we wandered around
and we were all confused and it was
ambiguous and finally we got the system
that we wanted now go tell the story as
if we went directly from point A to
point B and people will be able to
understand that a whole lot better than
trying to recount all the wanderings
that you do you can do that or you can
just throw everything away and then redo
that four hours it'll take you half an
hour and it'll be a clear set of we
change the structure in these kind of
ways which makes it easy to change the
behavior in these kinds of ways try that
as an experiment if it doesn't change
anything it doesn't change anything but
who knows now I guess the regular
question about AI because you Sur have
seen this many said that programmers
among other roles are going to disappear
they say all sorts of things about AI
but I know that you currently working
for a startup which offers Legacy
modernization which makes use of AI to
provide its services so you at least
have some contact with this I also have
a personal project called
renant so we can talk about both of
those okay and the thing is you know you
of course wrote the book tidy first for
humans not AI systems so what is your
view on the role of AI in software
development you know will programmers
become a role of the p
you know will AI enable everybody to
become a programmer or something else
everybody doesn't want to be a
programmer that's the key point so as an
old person I have seen this story told
over and over and over and over and over
again and that's what Cobalt there were
these main frames and you program them
in Assembly Language and the business
people wanted the computers to do things
but they couldn't get the programmers to
make the computers do the thing and then
Along Came Cobalt and now regular
business people will be able to write
their own
systems well it turns out that there's
more to writing a system than kind of
knowing what you want it to do it's an
actual discipline there's skills
involved if you don't have those skills
disaster results and then that same I
wasn't around for the cball thing
because that's 1960 I was just born but
that same impulse
you know today it was no code two years
ago a year ago it was no code now we
don't need programmers anymore anybody
can write their own software we have no
code well AI is it's just the next level
up of
abstraction there's some fundamental
amount of information you have to give
the system so you can't just say to an
AI write me a profitable application
there's not enough information in that
prompt so somebody has to say what the
system has to do and as soon as somebody
has to say what the system has to do
your programming whether it looks
exactly like programming or not and I am
using various llms right now and it
feels like programming but it's kind of
programming with chopsticks in a
blackened room wearing scheme gloves
you're like H I don't like you know here
here's this somebody asked my sister the
question and I just came back a terrible
answer how do I fix that and I'm like oh
I don't know do I change the prompt do
I blah blah but it's still programming
and then some final questions this are
questions I'm really curious about so
the first one is that you know you have
brought lots of ideas to the software
industry so the most famous ones test D
and development extreme programming
patterns and then there was the 3x
explore expand extract and then now that
is tidy Fest do you see all of them as
part of overarching method or theory of
software development so I wouldn't say
theory in a in a mathematical kind of
sense I would say there's a very human
thing that I have been trying to achieve
my whole career which is to help Geeks
feel safe in the world people with this
kind of geeky mindset often times feel
very
uncomfortable unsafe in perfectly
ordinary situations like at a cocktail
party oh God I hate being at cocktail
parties because I I'm always like am I
talking too much am I not talking enough
I try to talk to somebody
else Well turns out that that's a skill
learning to feel safe in that
environment is a skill and it's a
learnable skill and I'm around people on
a regular basis for whom this doesn't
even seem to be a problem but
it is for me so that sense of I want to
feel safe when I'm actually safe and I
want to feel unsafe when I'm actually
unsafe say I'm making some change to the
system and is there some side effect to
this and I don't know all right I want
to have new skills so that I actually am
safe I'm working in a safe way so that I
can feel safe so I can go home on the
weekends and feel good and I can
feel a sense of confidence and
accomplishment when I go home at night I
want to have those feelings so sometimes
it's the skills of learning to actually
engage in situations that felt unsafe
but were unsafe and sometimes it's
learning skills to be safe like
separating behavior and structure
changes oh life changer just the amount
of anxiety goes down so much when I'm
willing to take that extra
step so I would say my unifying theory
of software development is the
programmers are people too I noticed you
know reading your writings on the web
and your experiences that the thing you
blog about and now that you're writing
on your substack account it seems to me
that you are one of those people that
keeps re-evaluating what he used to
think and see try to see those in a new
light somehow and maybe improve yeah
it's an obsession it's not necessarily
healthy but I can't stop it so I may as
well try and uh get the leverage out of
it that I can based on that have you
found anything that you thought or wrote
in the past that you now consider to be
wrong wrong in the sense of I wouldn't
give this advice again let me give you a
concrete example I'm a big believer in
small batches so if you're going to to
do continuous integration the ultimate
of small batches is to take one poll
request at a
time and run it through the integration
process I have a team that I worked with
I've worked with for 20 years and 25
years in
Switzerland and their integration
process took 15 or 20 minutes and diffs
were piling up throughout the day and so
they you know if the principle was well
the small batches you have to do one
diff at a time it turns out that they
started batching their diffs and the
latency the waiting time went way way
down for everybody and the the whole
company started working better so that's
counter to the principle of flow of
small
batches but practically speaking I mean
the the long-term solution is to make
sure that the the integration process
doesn't take 15 minutes which is a
longer term more difficult decision so
was I wrong to recommend the principle
of low to that team I don't think so but
that's only one principle and there are
other principles involved too so I would
say there there are times when I've
missed context like that for sure yeah
but just like flat out oh that's a bad
idea I don't I don't I don't run across
those and my last question this is about
your Canon tdd so I think you published
that in your substock as well yes now
looking at that at the the graph you
created there there is no Tiding first
mentioned so why is that because that's
not part of the tdd workflow tdd is very
specific and and that was the point of
that article was people would complain
about tdd has become this political hot
but
I don't understand you can't make me
right test man I'm not trying to make
you right test I'm saying I'm
predicting your experience if you work
in this particular workflow and if
that's not your experience and I'm wrong
in my prediction it's fine do something
else I I don't care but many of the
criticisms were just of some other
workflow so people would say well I
don't I don't like having to write a 100
tests before I can write any code I'm
like well that's not what it says so
that's why I tried to lay it out I'm not
saying this is how you should program
I'm saying if you're criticizing tdd and
you're criticizing something that isn't
this then you're criticizing something
else entirely okay Kent I think we reach
the end of of this conversation thank
you very much and is there anything that
we miss that you would like to mention
so subscribe to the newsletter tidy
first. substack
docomond of tokens and fine tunes models
based on those called rent
aent so rent accent. to check out on
progress on that and there's some
interesting early returns for that thank
you so much for the very prepared
interview Javan I really appreciate that
thank you k for actually coming to the
show it's been a a real pleasure for me
and we came to the end this is Joan
aspon for software engineering radio
thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at
SE-R to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under creative comons
license
2.5 thanks for listening